<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Olivier Gimenez</title>
    <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://oliviergimenez.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Olivier Gimenez 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 13:07:40 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/sharon-mccutcheon-62vi3TG5EDg-unsplash_small.jpg</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human-dolphin interactions</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/project/interact/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 13:07:40 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/project/interact/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large carnivores monitoring</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/project/carnivores/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 13:07:40 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/project/carnivores/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Large carnivores are difficult to monitor in the field: they are elusive and live at low densities over wide areas. With their recent recovery in Europe,
large carnivores are having increasing interactions with human activities. We contribute to the estimation of their abundance and distribution by applying
and developing methods that make optimal use of available data. We are also working on applying science-based management using the structured
decision making
framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ongoing projects are mostly led by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/#current&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Master students, PhDs and post-docs&lt;/a&gt;: Julie Louvrier worked on tools to infer the
distribution of large carnivores in France and Norway; Loreleï Guéry in her post-doc studied population dynamics of lynx in Switzerland using
spatially-explicit closed and open capture-recapture models; Vincenzo Gervasi&amp;rsquo;s post-doc aimed at assessing the
determinants of conflicts on large carnivores in Europe and build trans-boundary management tools for wolves (France-Italy) and wolverines (Sweden-Norway); Nina Santostasi in her PhD is developing
demographic models for studying hybridizing species, with wolves in Italy as as case study; Lorena Mansilla in her PhD is developing capture-recapture models to assess the population dynamics of social species; Sarah Bauduin&amp;rsquo;s post-doc aims at developing a spatially-explicit agent-based model and software program for assessing lynx viability in France; Lucile Marescot&amp;rsquo;s post-doc aims at developing multispecies occupancy models for large carnivores and their preys.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multispecies demography</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/project/democom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 13:07:40 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/project/democom/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical ecology</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/project/methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 13:07:40 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/project/methods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Trained in mathematics and statistics, I work in 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cefe.cnrs.fr/fr/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;an ecology and evolution lab&lt;/a&gt; which allowed me to develop a bottomless taste for questions in 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://rsbl.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/10/12/20140698&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;statistical ecology&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I often resort to 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/#books&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;state-space models&lt;/a&gt;, and hidden Markov models (
&lt;a href=&#34;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23160641/my-pubs/Gimenezetal2014.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23160641/my-pubs/Gimenezetal2012TPB.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) in particular, to develop statistical methods for capture-recapture, occupancy and integrated models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We address questions in conservation biology to assess species viability, in ecology to study the effect of climate change on animal demography, in evolution to examine life-history tactics and individual heterogeneity and in wildlife management to develop strategies for conservation and conflict mitigation. To account for the human dimension related to these questions, I recently went back to the university to study sociology. A nice illustration of this interdisciplinary work is 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/#current&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gilles Maurer&amp;rsquo;s PhD&lt;/a&gt; combining anthropology, demography, economics and genetics to better understand the interactions between captive and wild population of Asian elephants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m doing my best to teach statistics (including the Bayesian way) to the students of the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.masters-biologie-ecologie.com/blog/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ecology and Evolution Master in Montpellier&lt;/a&gt;. We also make efforts to structure the community in France through our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/gdrecostat/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;national research group in statistical ecology&lt;/a&gt;. Last but not least, every year our team organizes 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://multievent.sciencesconf.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;workshops&lt;/a&gt; to diffuse the methods we develop.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terrestrial transport infrastructures, Lynx population viability and mitigation strategies</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/project/lynx/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 13:07:40 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/project/lynx/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Socio-ecological management of large carnivores</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/project/sciencepolicy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2017 13:07:40 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/project/sciencepolicy/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
