<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>management | Olivier Gimenez</title>
    <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/tags/management/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://oliviergimenez.github.io/tags/management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>management</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Olivier Gimenez 2024</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/flyfishing.jpg</url>
      <title>management</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/tags/management/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>DISCAR</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/my-project/external-project/discar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/my-project/external-project/discar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Context&lt;/em&gt;. Conservation and the sustainable use of biodiversity and ecosystem services largely depend on the successful management of ecological populations, which in turn depend on our knowledge and our ability to understand and predict how the structure and dynamics of ecological populations respond to changes in their environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rationale and aim&lt;/em&gt;. Despite its importance, the quantification of the effects of anthropic pressures on biodiversity is difficult and rarely undertaken because of the lack of species-specific ecological data and/or human pressures and activities, and the complexity and lack of transfer of analytical methods needed to evaluate these long-term consequences. The DISCAR (DIS = disturbance, CAR = carnivores) project aims at providing an operational framework with analytical tools for assessing the impacts or population consequences of human pressures, and showcasing it with case studies in applied conservation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Case study&lt;/em&gt;. In DISCAR, we will use small carnivores in French mainland and overseas territories as a case study to assess the population consequences or impacts of human pressures on animal populations. Why small carnivores? Because these species hold important roles in ecosystems, such as influencing ecosystem structure and providing numerous ecosystem services, including pest/disease control and seed dispersal. Small carnivore species also respond to ecosystem perturbation in a fast, measurable, and interpretable way and therefore can be used as sentinels of global change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Objectives&lt;/em&gt;. DISCAR will connect the fields of bioenergetics and demographic modeling in an integrated framework to assess human pressures on biodiversity, and to characterize then predict the impacts on small carnivores. DISCAR will identify key parameters underlying coupling between pressures and impacts, and will make recommendations for stakeholders in terms of monitoring and mitigation strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Work packages&lt;/em&gt;. We will i) assemble a unique dataset on small carnivores including their ecology, bioenergetic requirements, demography and human pressures, ii) quantify and characterize the impacts of interacting pressures on populations, and iii) forecast the fate of populations to assess their viability under various scenarios of pressures and mitigation to help devise sound conservation strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Consortium&lt;/em&gt;. To achieve these objectives, we have gathered international experts in ecological modelling and small carnivores who will develop and transfer an analytical framework for quantification, characterization and prediction of the impacts of pressures on populations. These experts are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Olivier Gimenez – CNRS (France)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sandrine Ruette – OFB (France)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cassie Speakman – CESAB/FRB (Australia)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Courtney Marneweck – Giraffe Conservation Foundation (South Africa)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patrick Giraudoux – Université Bourgogne Franche-Comté (France)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Isabel Smallegange - Newcastle University (UK)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sébastien Devillard – Université Claude Bernard Lyon 1 (France)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cara Gallagher - University of Potsdam (Allemagne)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sarah Cubaynes – EPHE (France)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John Fryxell – University of Guelph (Canada)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elizabeth McHuron – University of Washington (USA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rob Salguero-Gomez – University of Oxford (UK)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Katrinas Davis – University of Oxford (UK)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marie-Lazarine Poulle – Université Reims Champagne Ardenne (France)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Christophe Duchamp – OFB (France)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kévan Rastello – University of Victoria (Canada)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sarah Bull – University of Oxford (UK)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simon Lacombe – University of Montpellier (France)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maëlis Kervellec – University of Montpellier (France)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Funding&lt;/em&gt;. This project is funded by the French Foundation for Biodiversity Research (FRB) through 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fondationbiodiversite.fr/en/the-frb-in-action/programs-and-projects/le-cesab/discar/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cesab&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large carnivores monitoring</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/my-project/external-project/carnivores/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/my-project/external-project/carnivores/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Large carnivores are difficult to monitor in the field: they are elusive and live at low densities over wide areas. With their recent recovery in Europe,
large carnivores are having increasing interactions with human activities. We contribute to the estimation of their abundance and distribution by applying
and developing methods that make optimal use of available data. We are also working on applying science-based management using the structured
decision making framework. Past and ongoing projects were are are mostly led by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/#current&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Master students, PhDs and post-docs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terrestrial transport infrastructures, Lynx population viability and mitigation strategies</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/my-project/external-project/lynx/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/my-project/external-project/lynx/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New preprint by Julie Louvrier on forecasting species distribution</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/blog/preprintmecastat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/blog/preprintmecastat/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;We&amp;#39;ve been thinking a lot about &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/predictions?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#predictions&lt;/a&gt; in ecology lately. Here&amp;#39;s our modest crack at it &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/NU7ROWLFWF&#34;&gt;https://t.co/NU7ROWLFWF&lt;/a&gt; led by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/LouvrierJulie?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@LouvrierJulie&lt;/a&gt; w/ a mechanistic-statistical &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/SpeciesDistributionModel?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#SpeciesDistributionModel&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/forecast?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#forecast&lt;/a&gt; 🇫🇷🐺 expansion &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/ImperfectDetection?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#ImperfectDetection&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/WomenInSTEM?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#WomenInSTEM&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/ODEs?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#ODEs&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Bayes?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#Bayes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/D1n38edpDd&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/D1n38edpDd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Olivier Gimenez 🖖 (@oaggimenez) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/oaggimenez/status/1209009946743980032?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;December 23, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terrestrial transport infrastructures, Lynx population viability and mitigation strategies</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/blog/erc_lynx/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/blog/erc_lynx/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img style=&#34;float:left;margin-right:10px;margin-top:10px;width:200px;margin-bottom:5px&#34; src=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/jura.jpg&#34;&gt;
Our project `Avoid, reduce and compensate mortality risks of the Eurasian Lynx by collision with transport vehicles` aims to build on previous works on lynx population viability, collision risks while crossing terrestrial transport infrastructures and mitigation strategies. Our team will develop an operational tool upon which the technical operators will be able to rely on in the decision-making process for land-use planning. More details [here](https://sites.google.com/view/erclynx/) (in French).
&lt;p&gt;This applied research project gathers a group of various actors (public and private; researchers, wildlife managers and carnivore experts; infrastructure managers and road/transport planning experts) with the following objectives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maintaining functional connectivity between favorable lynx habitats and elaborating strategies for avoiding, reducing and compensating collision risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building a tool to reinforce and facilitation the implementation of land-use planning public policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To achieve these objectives, we will rely on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data on collisions (roads, railways) and external structural factors (ITT presence and their characteristics);&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A predictive statistical model to identify the zones with high probability of collision risks;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spatially-explicit individual-based population viability model (SEPVA) to predict extinction risks;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A user-friendly computer program implemented in R. We will follow a companion modeling approach to ensure the smooth adoption and use of this program by the actors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project will fill a gap between the academic research, the stakes of land planning, the lynx conservation and the needs of ITT managers/operators. We will contribute to the implementation of national public policies (TVB, SRCE/SRADDET, &amp;ldquo;Avoid, Reduce, Compensate&amp;rdquo; doctrine) by testing our approach on pilot sites in the Vosges and Jura areas. This project will benefit from the sharing of experiences and skills from our colleagues in Switzerland and Germany.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human-dolphin interactions</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/my-project/external-project/interact/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 00:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/my-project/external-project/interact/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multispecies demography</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/my-project/external-project/democom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/my-project/external-project/democom/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
