<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications | Olivier Gimenez</title>
    <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/publication/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://oliviergimenez.github.io/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Publications</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Olivier Gimenez 2023</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/flyfishing.jpg</url>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/publication/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Papers</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/publication/papers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/publication/papers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preprints&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moulherat S., L. Pautrel, G. Debat, M.-P. Etienne, L. Gendron, N. Hautière, J.-P. Tarel, G. Testud, O. Gimenez (2023). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3897/arphapreprints.e110040&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Biodiversity Monitoring with Intelligent Sensors: An Integrated Pipeline for Mitigating Animal-Vehicle Collisions&lt;/a&gt;. Arpha Preprint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bauduin S., Germain E., Zimmermann F., Idelberger S., Herdtfelder M., Heurich M., Kramer-Schadt S., Duchamp C., Drouet-Hoguet N., Morand A., Blanc L., Charbonnel A., Gimenez O. (2022). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2021.10.22.465393v2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Eurasian lynx populations in Western Europe: What prospects for the next 50 years?&lt;/a&gt; bioRxiv preprint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ghislain M., T. Bonnet, U. Godeau, O. Dehorter, O. Gimenez, P.-Y. Henry (2022). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ecoevorxiv.org/cyeb7/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Synchrony in adult survival is remarkably strong among common temperate songbirds across France.&lt;/a&gt; EcoEvoRxiv preprint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lauret V., O. Gimenez, H. Labach, N. Lescureux (2022). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/4875b/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Behind the scene of ecological expertise: the place of monitoring for biodiversity workers in the French Mediterranean Marine Protected Areas.&lt;/a&gt; SocArXiv preprint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rigoudy N., A. Benyoub, A. Besnard, C. Birck, Y. Bollet, Y. Bunz, J. Chiffard Carriburu, G. Caussimont, E. Chetouane, P. Cornette, A. Delestrade, N. De Backer, L. Dispan, M. Le Barh, J. Duhayer, J.-F. Elder, J.-B. Fanjul, J. Fonderflick, N. Froustey, M. Garel, W. Gaudry, A. Gérard, O. Gimenez, A. Hemery, A. Hemon, J.-M. Jullien, I. Malafosse, M. Marginean, V. Prunet, J. Rabault, M. Randon, A. Régnier, R. Ribière, J.-C. Ricci, S. Ruette, J. Sentilles, N. Siefert, B. Smith, G. Terpereau, W. Thuiller, A. Uzal, V. Vautrain, G. Dussert, B. Spataro, V. Miele, S. Chamaillé-Jammes (2023). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.03.15.484324v2.full&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The DeepFaune initiative: a collaborative effort towards the automatic identification of French fauna in camera-trap images.&lt;/a&gt; bioRxiv preprint&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Viollat L., M. Quéroué, K. Delord, O. Gimenez, C. Barbraud (2023). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.06.06.543885v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bottom-up effects and density dependence drive the dynamic of an antarctic seabird predator-prey system.&lt;/a&gt;  bioRxiv preprint&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desprez M., V. Miele, O. Gimenez (2023). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.10472&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nine tips for ecologists using machine learning.&lt;/a&gt; arXiv preprint&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Published&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lauret V., H. Labach, L. David, M. Authier, O. Gimenez (2023). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/oik.10270&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Using integrated multispecies occupancy models to map co-occurrence between bottlenose dolphins and fisheries in the Gulf of Lion, French Mediterranean Sea.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Oikos&lt;/em&gt; e10270.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Couturier T., S. Bauduin, G. Astruc, A. Blanck, C. Canonne, T. Chambert, J. Chiffard, A. Cosquer, S. Cubaynes, L. Curtet, E. Dortel, N. Drouet-Hoguet, C. Duchamp, C. Francesiaz, O. Grente, A. Jailloux, M. Kervellec, V. Lauret, J.-D. Lebreton, J. Louvrier, L. Marescot, R. Mathevet, M.-L. Navas, C. Perrot, N. Poulet, P.-Y. Quenette, M. Salas, G. Souchay, C. Vanpé, A. Besnard, O. Gimenez (2023). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/2688-8319.12245&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Building spaces of interactions between researchers and managers: Case studies with wildlife monitoring and conservation in France.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecological Solutions and Evidence&lt;/em&gt; 4:e12245.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Silk M., O. Gimenez (2023). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ecoevorxiv.org/h5d89/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Generation and applications of simulated datasets to integrate social network and demographic analyses.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 13:e9871.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kervellec M., C. Milleret, C. Vanpé, P.-Y. Quenette, J. Sentilles, S. Palazón, I. A. Jordana, R. Jato, M. M. Elósegui Irurtia, O. Gimenez (2023). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/KervellecBC2023.pdf&#34;&gt;Integrating opportunistic and structured non-invasive surveys with spatial capture-recapture models to map connectivity of the Pyrenean brown bear population.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Biological Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 278: 109875.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fernández-López, J., P. Acevedo, O. Gimenez (2023). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.revistaecosistemas.net/index.php/ecosistemas/article/view/2527&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;La unión hace la fuerza: modelos de distribución de especies integrando diferentes fuentes de datos.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecosistemas&lt;/em&gt; 32: 2527-2527.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rodrigues P., I. Dorresteijn, O. Gimenez (2023). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Rodrigues2023FoodWebs.pdf&#34;&gt;‘The human shield effect’: Human-wildlife co-occurrence patterns in the coffee forests of southwestern Ethiopia.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Food Webs&lt;/em&gt; 36: e00288.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Petridou M., J.F. Benson, O. Gimenez, Y. Iliopoulos, V. Kati (2023). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0006320723001982&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Do husbandry practices reduce depredation of free-ranging livestock? A case study with wolves in Greece.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Biological Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 283: 11009.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kleiven E.F., F. Barraquand, Gimenez O., J.-A. Henden, R. Anker Ims, E. M. Soininen, N. G. Yoccoz (2023). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s13253-023-00533-6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;A Dynamic Occupancy Model for Interacting Species with Two Spatial Scales.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;JABES&lt;/em&gt; In press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grente O., C. Duchamp, S. Bauduin, S. Chamaille-Jammes, N. Drouet-Hoguet, O. Gimenez (2023). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sciencepress.mnhn.fr/fr/periodiques/naturae/2023/5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tirs dérogatoires de loups en France : évaluation des effets sur les dommages aux troupeaux.&lt;/a&gt; Paru dans &lt;em&gt;Naturae&lt;/em&gt; numéro 5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tardy C., D. Ody, O. Gimenez, S. Planes (2023). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Tardy2023.pdf&#34;&gt;Abundance of fin whales (Balaenoptera physalus) in the north-western Mediterranean Sea, using photo-identification and microsatellite genotyping.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Marine Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 44:e12737.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Petridou M., J.F. Benson, O. Gimenez, V. Kati (2023). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mdpi.com/1424-2818/15/2/184&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Spatiotemporal Patterns of Wolves, and Sympatric Predators and Prey Relative to Human Disturbance in Northwestern Greece.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Diversity&lt;/em&gt; 15:184.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frost F., R. McCrea, R. King, O. Gimenez, E. Zipkin (2023). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s42519-022-00302-7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Integrated Population Models: Achieving Their Potential.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Journal of Statistical Theory and Practice&lt;/em&gt; 17:6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lauret V., H. Labach, D. Turek, S. Laran, O. Gimenez (2022). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zslpublications.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/acv.12815&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Integrated spatial models foster complementarity between monitoring programmes in producing large‐scale bottlenose dolphin indicators.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Animal Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 26: 228-238.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vanpé C., B. Piédallu, P.-Y. Quenette, J. Sentilles, G. Queney, S. Palazón, I. A. Jordana, R. Jato, M. M. Elósegui Irurtia, J. Solà de la Torre, O. Gimenez (2022). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://peercommunityjournal.org/articles/10.24072/pcjournal.199/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Estimating abundance of a recovering transboundary brown bear population with capture-recapture models.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Peer Community Journal&lt;/em&gt; 2:e71.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adamantopoulou S., A. A. Karamanlidis, P. Dendrinos, O. Gimenez (2022). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-03718409v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Citizen science indicates significant range recovery and defines new conservation priorities for Earth&amp;rsquo;s most endangered pinniped in Greece.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Animal Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 26: 115-125.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naciri, M, J Aars, MA Blanchet, O. Gimenez, S Cubaynes (2022). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fevo.2022.920481/full&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Reproductive senescence in polar bears in a variable environment&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Frontiers in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez O., M. Kervellec, J.-B. Fanjul, A. Chaine, L. Marescot, Y. Bollet, C. Duchamp (2021) 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://computo.sfds.asso.fr/published-202204-deeplearning-occupancy-lynx/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Trade-off between deep learning for species identification and inference about predator-prey co-occurrence: Reproducible R workflow integrating models in computer vision and ecological statistics.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Computo&lt;/em&gt;. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.57750/yfm2-5f45&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.57750/yfm2-5f45&lt;/a&gt;. Data and code 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/oliviergimenez/computo-deeplearning-occupany-lynx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grente O., T. Saubusse, Gimenez O., E. Marboutin, C. Duchamp (2022). 
&lt;a href=&#34;%28https://ecoevorxiv.org/n8rzg/%29&#34;&gt;Wolf depredation hotspots in France: Clustering analyses accounting for livestock availability.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Biological Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 267: 109495.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gervasi V., J. Linnell, T. Berce, L. Boitani, B. Cretois, P. Ciucci, C. Duchamp, A. Gastineau, O. Grente, D. Hilfiker, D. Huber, Y. Iliopoulos, A. Karamanlidis, F. Marucco, Y. Mertzanis, P. Mannil, H. Norberg, N. Pagon, L. Pedrotti, P.-Y. Quenette, S. Reljic, V. Salvatori, T. Talvi, M. von Arx, Gimenez O. (2021). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gervasietal2021GEC.pdf&#34;&gt;Ecological correlates of large carnivore depredation on sheep in Europe&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Global Ecology and Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 30: e01798.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kazakou E., Fried G., Cheptou P.-O., and Gimenez O. (2021). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ece3.8038&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Does seed mass drive interspecies variation in the effect of management practices on weed demography?&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 00: 1– 9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maurer G., Gimenez O., Mulot B., and Lescureux N. (2021). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/pan3.10247&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Under pressure: How human-wild-captive elephant social-ecological system in Laos is teetering due to global forces and sociocultural changes.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;People and Nature&lt;/em&gt; 3: 1047-1063.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rounsevell M.D.A., A. Arneth, C. Brown, W.W.L. Cheung, O. Gimenez, I. Holman, P. Leadley, C. Luján, S. Mahevas, I. Maréchaux, R. Pélissier, P. H. Verburg, G. Vieilledent, B.A. Wintle, Y-J Shin (2021). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Rounsevell2021OneEarth.pdf&#34;&gt;Identifying uncertainties in scenarios and models of socio-ecological systems in support of decision-making.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;One Earth&lt;/em&gt; 4: 967-985.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tavecchia G., O. Gimenez, R. Choquet, A. Rotger, D. Oro, S. Tenan, A. Sanz-Aguilar (2021). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Tavecchia2021BiolCons.pdf&#34;&gt;The trap of hidden processes: Why ‘quick &amp;amp; dirty’methods to estimate mortality are not always good. A comment to De Pascalis et al.(2020).&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Biological Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 256: 109057.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Santostasi N. L., O. Gimenez, R. Caniglia, E. Fabbri, L. Molinari, W. Reggioni, P. Ciucci (2021). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://wildlife.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/jwmg.22038&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Estimating Admixture at the Population Scale: Taking Imperfect Detectability and Uncertainty in Hybrid Classification Seriously.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Journal of Wildlife Management&lt;/em&gt; 85: 1031-1046.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zriki G., R. Blatrix, D. J. Bicout, O. Gimenez, A.‐S. Soulié, L. Dadu, D. Degueldre, G. Chiron, N. Sleeckx, L. Roy (2021). Population‐level impact of native arthropod predators on the poultry red mite Dermanyssus gallinae. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Experimental Zoology Part A: Ecological and Integrative Physiology&lt;/em&gt; 335: 552-563.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Miele V., S. Dray, O. Gimenez (2021) 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-03142486/document&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Images, écologie et deep learning.&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sfecologie.org/regard/r95-fev-2021-miele-dray-gimenez-deep-learning/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Regard 95&lt;/a&gt; de la Société Française d&amp;rsquo;Ecologie et d&amp;rsquo;Evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turek, D., C. Wehrhahn, Gimenez O. (2021). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2007.10163&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bayesian Non-Parametric Detection Heterogeneity in Ecological Models.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Environmental and Ecological Statistics&lt;/em&gt; 28: 355-381.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lauret V., Labach H., Authier M., Gimenez O. (2021). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Lauretetal2021Ecology.pdf&#34;&gt;Combining single- and repeated-visit occupancy models to make the best of monitoring surveys.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 102: e03535.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gamelon M, Baubet E., Besnard A., Gaillard J.-M., Lebreton J.-D., Touzot L., Veylit L., Gimenez O. (2021). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/ecog.05738&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Efficient use of harvest data: An integrated population model for exploited animal populations.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecography&lt;/em&gt; 44: 1296-1310.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Labach H., Azzinari C., Barbier M., Cesarini C., Daniel B., David L., Dhermain F., Di-Méglio N., Guichard B., Jourdan J., Robert N., Roul M., Tomasi N., Gimenez O. (2022). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Labachetal2021MMS.pdf&#34;&gt;Distribution and abundance of bottlenose dolphin (Tursiops truncatus) over the French Mediterranean continental shelf.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Marine Mammal Science&lt;/em&gt; 38: 212-222.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barraquand F., Gimenez O. (2021). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.02145&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fitting stochastic predator-prey models using both population density and kill rate data&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Theoretical Population Biology&lt;/em&gt; 138: 1-27.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cubaynes S., Aars J., Yoccoz N.G., Pradel R., Wiig Ø, Ims R.A., Gimenez O. (2021). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/ece3.7296&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Modeling the demography of species providing extended parental care: A capture-recapture approach with a case study on Polar Bears (Ursus maritimus).&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 11: 3380-3392.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quéroué M., C. Barbraud, F. Barraquand, D. Turek, K. Delord, N. Pacoureau, Gimenez O. (2021). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Queroueetal2021EM.pdf&#34;&gt;Multispecies integrated population model reveals bottom-up dynamics in a seabird predator-prey system&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecological Monographs&lt;/em&gt; 91: e01459.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grente O., C. Duchamp, S. Bauduin, T. Opitz, S. Chamaillé-Jammes, N. Drouet-Hoguet, O. Gimenez (2020) 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-02992939/file/Grente2020FauneSauvage.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tirs dérogatoires de loups en France: état des connaissances et des enjeux pour la gestion des attaques aux troupeaux.&lt;/a&gt; Paru dans &lt;em&gt;Faune Sauvage&lt;/em&gt; numéro 327.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bischof R., C. Milleret, P. Dupont, J. Chipperfield, M. Tourani, A. Ordiz, P. de Valpine, D. Turek, J. A. Royle, Gimenez O., Ø. Flagstad, M. Åkesson, L. Svensson, H. Brøseth, J. Kindberg (2020). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Bischof2020PNAS.pdf&#34;&gt;Estimating and forecasting spatial population dynamics of apex predators using transnational genetic monitoring.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 117:30531-30538.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vitet C., P. Duncan, Gimenez O., C. Mabika, S. Chamaillé‐Jammes (2020). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/ecs2.3288&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Plains zebras bring evidence that dilution and detection effects may not always matter behaviorally and demographically.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecosphere&lt;/em&gt; 11: e03288.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bauduin S., O. Grente, N.L. Santostasi, P. Ciucci, C. Duchamp, Gimenez O. (2020). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0304380020302799&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;An individual-based model to explore the impacts of lesser-known social dynamics on wolf populations.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecological Modelling&lt;/em&gt; 433: 109209.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McClintock B.T., R. Langrock, Gimenez O., E. Cam, D.L. Borchers, R. Glennie, T. A. Patterson (2020). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/ele.13610&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Uncovering ecological state dynamics with hidden Markov models.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecology Letters&lt;/em&gt; 23: 1878-1903.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genovart M., Gimenez O., A. Bertolero, R. Choquet, D. Oro, R. Pradel (2020). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-020-75259-3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Decrease in social cohesion in a colonial seabird under a perturbation regime.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Scientific reports&lt;/em&gt; 10: 18720.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Santostasi N.L., Ciucci P., Bearzi G., Bonizzoni S., Gimenez O. (2020). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Santostasietal2020EcolModel.pdf&#34;&gt;Assessing the dynamics of hybridization through a matrix modelling approach.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecological Modelling&lt;/em&gt; 431: 109120.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chero G., Pradel R., Derville S., Bonneville C., Gimenez O., Garrigue C. (2020). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Cheroetal2020MEPS.pdf&#34;&gt;Reproductive capacity of an endangered and recovering population of humpback whales in the Southern Hemisphere.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Marine Ecology Progress Series&lt;/em&gt; 643: 219-227.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Milleret C., Dupont P., Chipperfield J., Turek D., Brøseth H., Gimenez O., de Valpine P., Bischof R. (2020). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/ecs2.3172&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Estimating abundance with interruptions in data collection using open population spatial capture–recapture models.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecosphere&lt;/em&gt; 11( 6):e03172.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louvrier L., Papaïx J., Duchamp C., Gimenez O. (2020). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Louvrier2020SpatialStatistics.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;A mechanistic-statistical species distribution model to explain and forecast wolf (Canis lupus) colonization in South-Eastern France.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Spatial Statistics&lt;/em&gt; 36: 100428.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marescot L., Lyet A., Singh R., Carter N., Gimenez O. (2019). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Marescot2019Ecography.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Inferring wildlife poaching in southeast Asia with multispecies dynamic occupancy models.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecography&lt;/em&gt; 42: 1–12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gamble A., Garnier R., Chambert T., Gimenez O., Boulinier T. (2020). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gamble2019Ecology.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Next generation serology: integrating cross-sectional and capture-recapture approaches to infer disease dynamics.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 101:e02923.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barraquand F., Gimenez O. (2019). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Barraquand2019EcolModel.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Integrating multiple data sources to fit matrix population models for interacting species.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecological Modelling&lt;/em&gt; 411: 108713.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez O., Gatti S., Duchamp C., Germain E., Laurent A., Zimmermann F., Marboutin E. (2019). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/ece3.5668&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Spatial density estimates of Eurasian lynx (Lynx lynx) in the French Jura and Vosges Mountains&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 9: 11707-11715.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Renner, I.W., Louvrier J., Gimenez O. (2019). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/615583v3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Combining multiple data sources in species distribution models while accounting for spatial dependence and overfitting with combined penalized likelihood maximization&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 10: 2118-2128.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonnet‐Lebrun A. , Karamanlidis A. A., de Gabriel Hernando M. , Renner I. and O. Gimenez (2019). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/BonnetLebrun2019AnCons.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Identifying priority conservation areas for a recovering brown bear population in Greece using citizen science data.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Animal Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 23: 83-93&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Donfrancesco V., Ciucci P., [14 authors], Gimenez O., [28 authors] and Mukherjee N. (2019). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/DonFrancescoetal2019Frontiers.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Unravelling the Scientific Debate on How to Address Wolf-Dog Hybridization in Europe.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Frontiers in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 7:175. doi: 10.3389/fevo.2019.00175.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gervasi V., Linnell J.D.C., Brøseth H., Gimenez O. (2019). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gervasi2019JAE.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Failure to coordinate management in transboundary populations hinders the achievement of national management goals: The case of wolverines in Scandinavia.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Journal of Applied Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 56: 1905-1915.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lok T., Hassell C.J., Piersma T., Pradel R. Gimenez O. (2019). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Loketal2019EE.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Accounting for heterogeneity when estimating stopover duration, timing and population size of red knots along the Luannan Coast of Bohai Bay, China.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 9: 6176–6188.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le Bot T., A. Lescroël, J. Fort, C. Péron, O. Gimenez, P. Provost, D. Grémillet (2019). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/LeBotetal2019.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Fishery discards do not compensate natural prey shortage in Northern gannets from the English Channel.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Biological Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 236: 375-384.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dorinda Marie Folio, J. Aars, O. Gimenez, A. E. Derocher, Ø. Wiig and S. Cubaynes (2019). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Folioetal2019.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;How many cubs can a mum nurse? Maternal age and size influence litter size in polar bears.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Biology Letters&lt;/em&gt;. 15: 20190070.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dupont P., Milleret C, Gimenez O., Bischof R (2019). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/2041-210X.13158&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Population closure and the bias‐precision trade‐off in spatial capture–recapture.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 10: 661-672.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Santostasi N.L., P. Ciucci, R. Caniglia, E. Fabbri, L. Molinari, W. Reggioni, Gimenez O. (2019). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/ece3.4819&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Use of hidden Markov capture–recapture models to estimate abundance in the presence of uncertainty: Application to the estimation of prevalence of hybrids in animal populations.&lt;/a&gt; * Ecology and evolution * 9: 744-755.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez O., L. Mansilla, M.J. Klaich, M.A. Coscarella, S.N. Pedraza, E.A. Crespo (2019). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenezetal2019EcolModel.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Inferring animal social networks with imperfect detection.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecological Modelling&lt;/em&gt;. 401: 69-74.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Melovski, D., Von Arx, M., Avukatov, V., Breitenmoser-Würsten, C., Đurović, M., Elezi, R., Gimenez O., &amp;hellip; , Breitenmoser, U. (2019). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Melovskietal2019OryxBalkanLynx.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Using questionnaire surveys and occupancy modelling to identify conservation priorities for the Critically Endangered Balkan lynx Lynx lynx balcanicus.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Oryx&lt;/em&gt;. 54: 706-714.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benhaiem S., Marescot L., East M. L., Kramer-Schadt S., Gimenez O., Lebreton J.-D. Hofer H. (2018). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s42003-018-0197-1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Slow recovery from a disease epidemic in the spotted hyena, a keystone social carnivore&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Communications Biology&lt;/em&gt;. 201: 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louvrier J., Chambert T., Marboutin E., Gimenez O. (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Louvrieretal2018EcolModel.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Accounting for misidentification and heterogeneity in occupancy studies using hidden Markov models.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecological Modelling&lt;/em&gt;. 387: 61-69.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Santostasi N. L., Bonizzoni S., Gimenez O., Eddy L., Bearzi G. (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Santostasietal2018AC.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Common dolphins in the Gulf of Corinth are Critically Endangered.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Aquatic Conserv: Mar Freshw Ecosys&lt;/em&gt;. 31: 101-109. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/aqc.2963&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/aqc.2963&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louvrier J., Molinari‐Jobin A., Kéry M., Chambert T., Miller D., Zimmermann F., Marboutin E., Molinari P., Mueller O., Cerne R., Gimenez O. (2019). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Louvrier_et_al-2018-Conservation_Biology.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Use of ambiguous detections to improve estimates from species distribution models.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Conservation Biology&lt;/em&gt;. 33: 185-195.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benhaiem S., Marescot L., Hofer H., East M.L., Lebreton J.-D., Kramer-Schadt S., Gimenez O. (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2018.00197/full&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Robustness of eco-epidemiological capture-recapture parameter estimates to variation in infection state uncertainty.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Frontiers in Veterinary Science&lt;/em&gt; 5: 197.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez O., Lebreton J.‐D., Choquet R., Pradel R. (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenezetal2018MEE.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;R2ucare: An r package to perform goodness‐of‐fit tests for capture–recapture models.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 9: 1749–1754.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salguero‐Gomez R., Violle C., Gimenez O., Childs D. (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/SGetalFE2018.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Delivering the promises of trait‐based approaches to the needs of demographic approaches, and vice versa.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Functional Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 32: 1424–1435.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bancila R. I., Pradel R., Choquet R., Plaiasu R., Gimenez O. (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/BancilaetalEE2018.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Using temporary emigration to inform movement behaviour of cave‐dwelling invertebrates: a case study of a cave harvestman species.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecological Entomology&lt;/em&gt; 43: 551-559.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chandelier M., Steuckardt A., Mathevet R., Diwersy S., Gimenez O. (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Chandelieretal2018BC.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Content analysis of newspaper coverage of wolf recolonization in France using structural topic modeling&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Biological Conservationa&lt;/em&gt; 220: 254-261.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marescot L, Benhaiem S, Gimenez O. et al. (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/MarescotetaL2018FE.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Social status mediates the fitness costs of infection with canine distemper virus in Serengeti spotted hyenas.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Functional Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 32: 1237–1250.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barbraud C., Bertrand A., Bouchón M., Chaigneau A., Delord K., Demarcq H., Gimenez O., Torero M. G., Gutiérrez D., Oliveros-Ramos R., Passuni G., Tremblay Y., Bertrand S. (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Barbraudetal2018Ecography.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Density dependence, prey accessibility and prey depletion by fisheries drive Peruvian seabird population dynamics.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ecography&lt;/em&gt; 41: 1092-1102.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marzolin G., Gimenez O. (2018). 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://joss.theoj.org/papers/c93e42d092f6ed4f66e3951c89136690&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fitting a Gamma-Gompertz survival model to capture-recapture data collected on free-ranging animal populations&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Open Source Software&lt;/em&gt;. 3(21): 216.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bearzi G., Gimenez O. (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Bearzi&amp;Gimenez2018.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Searching for meaning in marine mammal shared data.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ethics in Science and Environmental Politics&lt;/em&gt;. 18: 9-13.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamel S., Gaillard J.-M., Yoccoz N. G., Bassar R. D., Bouwhuis S., Caswell H., Douhard M., Gangloff E. J., Gimenez O., Lee P. C., Smallegange I. M., Steiner U. K., Vedde, O. and Vindenes Y. (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Hameletal2018Oikos.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt; General conclusion to the special issue Moving forward on individual heterogeneity.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Oikos&lt;/em&gt;. 127: 750–756.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desprez M., Gimenez O., McMahon C.R., Hindell M.A., Harcourt R.G. (2018).  &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Desprezetal2017JAE.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Optimizing lifetime reproductive output: Intermittent breeding as a tactic for females in a long-lived, multiparous mammal.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Journal of Animal Ecology&lt;/em&gt;. 87: 199–211.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bumb I., Garnier E., Coq S., Nahmani J., Del Rey Granado M., Gimenez O., E. Kazakou (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/BumbetalAnnBotany.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Traits determining the digestibility– decomposability relationships in species from Mediterranean rangelands&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Annals of Botany&lt;/em&gt;. 121: 459–469.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robardet E., Borel C., Moinet M., Jouan D., Wasniewski M., Barrat J., Boue F., Monchatre-Leroy E., Servat A., Gimenez O., Cliquet F., Picard-Meyer E. (2017). 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.plos.org/plosntds/article?id=10.1371/journal.pntd.0006048&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Long-term population surveys of two serotine bat (Eptesicus serotinus) colonies exposed to EBLV-1 (European Bat Lyssavirus type 1): Assessment of rabies transmission using capture-recapture models&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases&lt;/em&gt;. 11 (11), e0006048.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez O., E. Cam, J.-M. Gaillard (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/GimenezCamGaillard2017Oikos.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Individual heterogeneity and capture–recapture models: what, why and how?&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Oikos&lt;/em&gt;. 127: 664–686.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez O., J.-M. Gaillard (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenez&amp;Gaillard2017PopEcol.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Estimating individual fitness in the wild using capture–recapture data&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Population Ecology&lt;/em&gt;. 60: 101–109.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez O., C. Barbraud (2017). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenez&amp;Barbraud2017PopEcol.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dealing with many correlated covariates in capture–recapture models&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Population Ecology&lt;/em&gt;. 59: 287-291.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bertulli C.G., L. Guéry, N. McGinty, A. Suzuki, N. Brannan, T. Marques, M. H. Rasmussen, Gimenez O. (2017). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Bertullietal2017SEARES.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Capture-recapture abundance and survival estimates of three cetacean species in Icelandic coastal waters using trained scientist-volunteers&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Sea Research&lt;/em&gt;. 131: 22-31.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maurer G., Rashford B. S., Chanthavong V., Mulot B., Gimenez O. (2017). &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-017-13907-x&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Wild-captive interactions and economics drive dynamics of Asian elephants in Laos&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt;. DOI:10.1038/s41598-017-13907-x.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lieury N., Devillard S., Besnard A., Gimenez O., Hameau O., Ponchon C., Millon A. (2017). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Lieuryetal2017_BiolCons.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Designing cost-effective capture-recapture surveys for improving the monitoring of survival in bird populations&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biological Conservation&lt;/em&gt;. 214: 233-241.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tidière M., Lemaître J.-F., Pélabon C., Gimenez O. and Gaillard, J.-M. (2017). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Tidiereal2017JEB.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Evolutionary allometry reveals a shift in selection pressure on male horn size&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Evolutionary Biology&lt;/em&gt;. 30: 1826–1835.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lagrange P., Gimenez O., Doligez B., Pradel R., Garant D., Pelletier F., Bélisle M. (2017). &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ece3.3241/abstract&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Assessment of individual and conspecific reproductive success as determinants of breeding dispersal of female tree swallows: A capture-recapture approach&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt;. 7: 7334-7346.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louvrier, J., C. Duchamp, V. Lauret, E. Marboutin, S. Cubaynes, R. Choquet, C. Miquel, O. Gimenez (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Louvrieretal2017Ecography.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mapping and explaining wolf recolonization in France using dynamic occupancy models and opportunistic data&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecography&lt;/em&gt;. 41: 647-660.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Piédallu, B., P.-Y. Quenette, N. Bombillon, A. Gastineau, C. Miquel, O. Gimenez (2019). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Piedalluetal2017Oryx.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Determinants and patterns of habitat use by the brown bear Ursus arctos in the French Pyrenees revealed by occupancy modelling&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Oryx&lt;/em&gt;. 53: 334–343.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Santostasi, N.L., S. Bonizzoni, G. Bearzi, L. Eddy, O. Gimenez (2016). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Santostasietal2016PlosOne.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;A Robust Design Capture-Recapture Analysis of Abundance, Survival and Temporary Emigration of Three Odontocete Species in the Gulf of Corinth, Greece&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Plos One&lt;/em&gt;. 11(12): e0166650.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kazakou, E., G. Fried, J. Richarte, O. Gimenez, C. Violle and A. Metay (2016). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Kazakouetal2016BotanyLetters.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;A plant trait-based response-and-effect framework to assess vineyard inter-row soil management&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Botany Letters&lt;/em&gt;. 163: 373-388.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Péron, G., J.-M. Gaillard, C. Barbraud, C. Bonenfant, A. Charmantier, R. Choquet, T. Coulson, V. Grosbois, A. Loison, G. Marzolin, N. Owen-Smith, D. Pardo, F. Plard, R. Pradel, C. Toïgo, O. Gimenez (2016). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Peronetal2016_Evolution.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Evidence of reduced individual heterogeneity in adult survival of long-lived species&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Evolution&lt;/em&gt;. 70: 2909-2914.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abadi, F., C. Barbraud, O. Gimene (2017). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/abadi2016.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Integrated population modeling reveals the impact of climate on survival of juvenile emperor penguin&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Global Change Biology&lt;/em&gt;. 23: 1353-1359.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McCrea, R.S., B.J.T. Morgan, O. Gimenez (2017). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/McCreaetal2017JRSSC.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;A new strategy for diagnostic model assessment in capture-recapture&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series C&lt;/em&gt;. 66: 815-831.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tidière, M., J.-M. Gaillard, V. Berger, D.W.H. Müller, L. Bingaman Lackey, O. Gimenez, M. Clauss and J.-F. Lemaître (2016). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Tidi%C3%A8retal2016ScReports.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Comparative analyses of longevity and senescence reveal variable survival benefits of living in zoos across mammals&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt;. 6: 36361.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bearzi, G., S. Bonizzoni, N.L. Santostasi, N.B. Furey, L. Eddy, V.D. Valavanis, O. Gimenez (2016). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Bearzi_etal_inPress.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dolphins in a Scaled-Down Mediterranean: The Gulf of Corinth&amp;rsquo;s Odontocetes&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Advances in Marine Biology&lt;/em&gt;. 75: 297-331.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soldatini, C., Y.V. Albores-Barajas, B. Massa and O. Gimenez (2016). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Soldatinietal2016MEPS.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Forecasting ocean warming impacts on seabird demography: a case study on the European storm petrel&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Marine Ecology Progress Series&lt;/em&gt;. 552: 255–269.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gervasi, V., Brøseth, H, Gimenez, O., Nilsen, E.B., Odden, J., Flagstad, O. and J.D.C. Linnell (2016). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gervasietal2016_WildlifeBiology.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Sharing data improves monitoring of trans-boundary populations: the case of wolverines in central Scandinavia&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Wildlife Biology&lt;/em&gt;. 22: 95–106.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Piédallu, B., Quenette, P.-Y., Mounet, C., Lescureux, N., Borelli-Massines, M., Dubarry, E., Camarra, J.-J. &amp;amp; Gimenez, O. (2016). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Pi%C3%A9dalluetal2016-BiolCons.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Spatial variation in public attitudes towards brown bears in the French Pyrénées&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biological Conservation&lt;/em&gt;. 197: 90–97.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boulenger, C., A. Acou, O. Gimenez, F. Charrier, J. Tremblay &amp;amp; E. Feunteun (2016). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Boukengeretal2016fwb.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Factors underlying survival of yellow European eels in two unexploited eel sub-populations&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Freshwater Biology&lt;/em&gt;. 61: 947-962.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gager, Y., O. Gimenez, M. Teage O&amp;rsquo;Mara and Dina K.N. Dechmann (2016) &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gageretal2016BMCEcology.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Group size, survival and surprisingly short lifespan in socially foraging bats&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;BMC Ecology&lt;/em&gt;. 16:2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C.A. Bost, C. Cotté, P. Terray, C. Barbraud, C. Bon, K. Delord, O. Gimenez, Y. Handrich, Y. Naito, C. Guinet, H. Weimerskirch (2015). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Bostetal2015NatComm.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Large-scale climatic anomalies affect marine predator foraging behaviour and demography&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Nature Communications&lt;/em&gt;. 6: 8220.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tidière, M., J.-M. Gaillard, D.W.H. Müller, L. Bingaman Lackey, O. Gimenez, M. Clauss, J.-F. Lemaître (2015). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/tidiere2015.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Does sexual selection shape sex-differences in longevity and senescence patterns across vertebrates? A review and new insights from captive ruminants&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Evolution&lt;/em&gt;. 69: 3123–3140 .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mouquet, N., Lagadeuc, Y., Devictor, V., Doyen, L., Duputié, A., Eveillard, D., Faure, D., Garnier, E., Gimenez, O., Huneman, P., Jabot, F., Jarne, P., Joly, D., Julliard, R., Kéfi, S., Kergoat, G. J., Lavorel, S., Le Gall, L., Meslin, L., Morand, S., Morin, X., Morlon, H., Pinay, G., Pradel, R., Schurr, F. M., Thuiller, W., Loreau, M. (2015). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Mouquetetal2015JAE.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Predictive ecology in a changing world&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Applied Ecology.&lt;/em&gt; 52: 1293–1310.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gamelon, M., Gaillard, J.-M., Gimenez, O., Coulson, T., Tuljapurkar, S., Baubet, E. (2016). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gamelon%20et%20al.%202015_Oikos.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Linking demographic responses and life history tactics from longitudinal data in mammals&lt;/a&gt;. *Oikos. *125: 395–404.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karamanlidis, A.A., M. de Gabriel Hernando, L. Krambokoukis, O. Gimenez (2015). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Karamanlidisetal2015-Arcturos.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Evidence of a large carnivore population recovery: counting bears in Greece&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal for Nature Conservation&lt;/em&gt;. 27: 10-17.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bischof, R., H. Broseth, O. Gimenez (2016). &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/conl.12183/abstract&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Wildlife in a politically divided world: insularism inflates estimates of brown bear abundance&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Conservation Letters&lt;/em&gt;. 9: 122–130.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez, O., Buckland, S.T., Morgan, B.J.T., Bez, N., Bertrand, S., Choquet, R., Dray, S., Etienne, M.-P., Fewster, R., Gosselin, F., Mérigot, B., Monestiez, P., Morales, J., Mortier, F., Munoz, F., Ovaskainen, O., Pavoine, S., Pradel, R., Schurr, F.M., Thomas, L., Thuiller, W., Trenkel, V., de Valpine P., E. Rexstad (2015). &lt;a href=&#34;http://rsbl.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/10/12/20140698&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Statistical ecology comes of age&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biology Letters&lt;/em&gt;. 10: 20140698. &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/codes/suppmat.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Data and R codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tidière, M., J.-M. Gaillard, D.W.H. Müller, L. Bingaman Lackey, O. Gimenez, M. Clauss, J.-F. Lemaître (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Tidiereetal2014.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Males do not senesce faster in large herbivores with highly seasonal rut&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Experimental Gerontology&lt;/em&gt;. 60: 167–172.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Koons, D.N., F. Colchero, K. Hersey, and O. Gimenez (2015). &lt;a title=&#34;bison&#34; href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Koons%20et%20al%202015%20effects%20of%20climate%20density%20dependence%20and%20harvest%20on%20bison%20population%20dynamics.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Disentangling the effects of climate, density dependence, and harvest on an iconic large herbivore&amp;rsquo;s population dynamics&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecological Applications&lt;/em&gt; 25: 956–967.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gervasi, V., Brøseth, H., Gimenez, O., Nilsen, E., Linnell, J. (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ece3.1258/abstract&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The risks of learning: confounding detection and demographic trend when using count-based indices for population monitoring&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt;. 4: 4637–4648.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gamelon, M., Gimenez, O., Baubet, E., Coulson, T., Tuljapurkar, S., Gaillard, J.-M. (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gamelonetal2014AmNat.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Influence of Life-History Tactics on Transient Dynamics: A Comparative Analysis across Mammalian Populations&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;The American Naturalist&lt;/em&gt; 184: 673-683.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barnagaud, J.Y., Papaïx, J., Gimenez, O., Svenning, J.-C. (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Barnagaudetal2014.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dynamic spatial interactions between the native invader Brown-headed Cowbird and its hosts - a metacommunity approach&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Diversity and Distributions&lt;/em&gt;. 21: 511-522.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Orgeret, F, Garrigue, C., Gimenez, O., Pradel, R. (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Orgeretetal2014MEPS.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Robust assessment of population trends in marine mammals applied to the New Caledonia Humpback Whales&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Marine Ecology Progress Series&lt;/em&gt; 515: 265–273.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Koons, D.N., M. Gamelon, J.-M. Gaillard, L.M. Aubry, R.F. Rockwell, F. Klein, R. Choquet and O. Gimenez (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/KoonsetalMEE2014.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Methods for Studying Cause-Specific Senescence in the Wild&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 5: 924-933.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gamelon, M., S. Focardi, J.-M. Gaillard, O. Gimenez, C. Bonenfant, B. Franzetti, R. Choquet, F. Ronchi, E. Baubet, J.-F. Lemaître. (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/GamelonetalEvol2014.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Do age-specific survival patterns of wild boar fit current evolutionary theories of senescence?&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Evolution&lt;/em&gt;. 68: 3636–3643.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blanc, L., E. Marboutin, S. Gatti, F. Zimmermann and O. Gimenez (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Blancetal2014JAE.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Improving abundance estimation by combining capture-recapture and occupancy data: example with a large carnivore&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Applied Ecology&lt;/em&gt;. 51: 1733–1739.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez, O., L. Blanc, A. Besnard, R. Pradel, P. F. Doherty Jr, E. Marboutin and R. Choquet (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenezetal2014.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Fitting occupancy models with E-SURGE: hidden-Markov modelling of presence-absence data&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt;. 5: 592–597. &lt;a href=&#34;http://occupancyinesurge.wikidot.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Wiki&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lee, K.A., C. Huveneers, O. Gimenez, V. Peddemors, R.G. Harcourt (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Lee2014.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;To catch or to sight? A comparison of demographic parameter estimates obtained from mark-recapture and mark-resight models&lt;/a&gt;. *Biodiversity and Conservation.*23: 2781-2800.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soldatini, C., Y. V. Albores-Barajas, B. Massa and O. Gimenez (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Soldatini2014.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Climate Driven Life Histories: The Case of the Mediterranean Storm Petrel&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Plos One&lt;/em&gt; 9: e94526.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Santin-Janin, H., B. Hugueny, P. Aubry, D. Fouchet, O. Gimenez and D. Pontier (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/SantinJanin2014.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Accounting for Sampling Error When Inferring Population Synchrony from Time-Series Data: A Bayesian State-Space Modelling Approach with Applications&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Plos One&lt;/em&gt; 9: e87084.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hardouin, L. A., A. Robert, M. Nevoux, O. Gimenez, F. Lacroix and Y. Hingrat (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Hardouinetal_jpe12302.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Meteorological conditions influence short-term survival and dispersal in a reinforced bird population&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Applied Ecology&lt;/em&gt;. 51: 1494–1503.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desprez M., Harcourt R., Hindell M.A., Cubaynes S., Gimenez O., McMahon C.R. (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Desprez_et_al_2014%20-%20BiologyLetters.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Age-specific cost of first reproduction in female southern elephant seals&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biology Letters&lt;/em&gt; 10: 20140264.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cubaynes, S. C. Lavergne, O. Gimenez (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Cubaynesetal2014EES.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Fitting animal survival models with temporal random effects. &lt;em&gt;Environmental and Ecological Statistics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;* *21: 599–610. &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/codes/appendix.txt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lagrange, P., R. Pradel, M. Bélisle, O. Gimenez (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Lagrangeetal2014Ecology.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Estimating dispersal among numerous sites using capture-recapture data&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecology&lt;/em&gt;. 95: 2316-2323.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Souchay, G., O. Gimenez, G. Gauthier, R. Pradel (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/ACE-ECO-2013-628.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Variations in Band Reporting Rate and Implications for Kill Rate in Greater Snow Geese&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Avian Conservation and Ecology&lt;/em&gt;. 9: 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le Saout, S., S. Chollet, S. Chamaille-Jammes, L. Blanc, S. Padié, T. Verchère, J.A. Gaston, M. Gillingham, O. Gimenez, K.L. Parker, D. Picot, H. Verheyden, J.-L. Martin (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/LeSaout2014.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Understanding the Paradox of Deer Persisting at High Abundance in Heavily Browsed Habitats&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Wildlife Biology&lt;/em&gt;. 20: 122-135.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Millon, A., S.J. Petty, B. Little, O. Gimenez, T. Cornulier, X. Lambin (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Millonetal2014.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Deleterious effect of dampening prey cycle overrides the impact of climate change on predator dynamics: a long term demographic study on tawny owls&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Global Change Biology&lt;/em&gt;. 20: 1770–1781.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cole, D., B.J.T. Morgan, R.S. McCrea, R. Pradel, O. Gimenez, R. Choquet (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Coleetal2014.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Does Your Species Have Memory? Analysing Capture-Recapture Data with Memory Models&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt;. 4: 2124–2133.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abadi, F., C. Barbraud, D. Besson, J. Bried, P.-A. Crochet, K. Delord, J. Forcada, V. Grosbois, R. A. Phillipse, P. Sagar, P. Thompson, S. Waugh, H. Weimerskirch, A.G. Wood, O. Gimenez (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Abadietal2014EcolModelling.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Importance of accounting for phylogenetic dependence in multi-species mark–recapture studies&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecological Modelling&lt;/em&gt;. 273: 236-241.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frederiksen, M., Lebreton, J.-D., Pradel, R., Choquet, R. and O. Gimenez (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Frederiksenetal2013JAE.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Identifying links between vital rates and environment: a toolbox for the applied ecologist&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Applied Ecology&lt;/em&gt;. 51: 71-81.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marescot, L., Chapron, G., Chadès, I., Fackler, P., Duchamp, C., Marboutin, E. and O. Gimenez (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Marescotetal2013MEEwithappendices.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Complex decisions made simple: A primer on stochastic dynamic programming&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 4: 872-884. &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/2041-210X.12082/suppinfo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gamelon, M., M. Douhard, E. Baubet, O. Gimenez, S Brandt and J.-M. Gaillard (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gamelonetal2013BiologyLetters.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Fluctuating food resources influence developmental plasticity in wild boar&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biology Letters&lt;/em&gt; 9: 20130419.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desprez, M., McMahon, C., Hindell, M., Harcourt, R. and O. Gimenez (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/ece3846.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Known unknowns in an imperfect world: incorporating uncertainty in recruitment estimates using multi-event capture-recapture models&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 3: 4658-4668.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desprez, M., Crivelli, A.J., Lebel I., Massez G. and O. Gimenez (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Desprezetal2013EFF.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Demographic assessment of a stocking experiment in European Eels&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecology of Freshwater Fish&lt;/em&gt; 22: 412-420.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lamy, T., O. Gimenez, J.-P. Pointier, P. Jarne and P. David (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Lamyetal2013AmNat.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Metapopulation dynamics of species with cryptic life stages&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;The American Naturalist&lt;/em&gt; 181: 479-491. &lt;a href=&#34;http://datadryad.org/resource/doi:10.5061/dryad.s7v4b&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Madon, B., C. Garrigue, R. Pradel, O. Gimenez (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Madonetal2012MMS.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Transience in the humpback whale population of New Caledonia and implications for abundance estimation&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Marine Mammal Science&lt;/em&gt; 29: 669-678. &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/codes/mms610-sup-0002-AppendixS2.doc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gamelon, M., J.-M. Gaillard, E. Baubet, S. Devillard, L. Say, S. Brandt &amp;amp; O. Gimenez (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/GamelonetalJAE2013coinflipping.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The relationship between phenotypic variation among offspring and mother body mass in wild boar: Evidence of coin-flipping?&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Journal of Animal Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 82: 937-945.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choquet, R., A. Sanz-Aguilar, B. Doligez, E. Nogué, R. Pradel, L. Gustafsson and O. Gimenez (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Choquetetal2013MEE.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Estimating demographic parameters from capture-recapture data with dependence among individuals within clusters&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 4: 474-482.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Péron, G., Y. Ferrand, G. Leray and O. Gimenez (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Peronetal2013BiolCons.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Waterbird demography as indicator of wetland health: The French-wintering common snipe population&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biological Conservation&lt;/em&gt;. 164: 123-128&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolker, B., Gardner, B., Maunder, M., Berg, C., Brooks, M., Comita, L., Crone, E., Cubaynes, S., Davies, T., de Valpine, P., Ford, J., Gimenez, O., Kéry, M., Kim, E., Lennert-Cody, C., Magnusson, A., Martell, S., Nash, J., Nielsen, A., Regetz, J., Skaug, H., Zipkin, E. (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Bolkeretal2013MEE.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Strategies for fitting nonlinear ecological models in R, AD Model Builder, and BUGS&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 4: 501-512. &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.nceas.ucsb.edu/non-linear-modeling/projects&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Praud, A., O. Gimenez, G. Zanella, N. Pozzi, V. Antras, L. Meyer, B. Garin-Bastuji (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Praudetal2013.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Evaluation of five serological tests for the diagnosis of porcine brucellosis in French Polynesia&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Trop Anim Health Prod&lt;/em&gt; 45: 933-936&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bellan, S., O. Gimenez, R. Choquet and W. Getz (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Bellanetal2013MEE.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;A Hierarchical Distance Sampling Approach to Estimating Mortality Rates from Opportunistic Carcass Surveillance Data&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 4: 361-369&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;de Villemereuil, P., Gimenez, O., Doligez, B. (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/deVillemereuiletal2013MEE.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Comparing parent-offspring regression with Frequentist and Bayesian animal models to estimate heritability in wild populations: a simulation study for Gaussian and binary traits&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 4: 260-275. &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/2041-210X.12011/suppinfo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cam, E., O. Gimenez, R. Alpizar-Jara, L. M. Aubry, M. Authier, E. G. Cooch, D. N. Koons, W. A. Link, J.-Y. Monnat, J. D. Nichols, J. J. Rotella, J. A. Royle, R. Pradel (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Cametal2012Oikos.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Looking for a needle in a haystack: inference about individual fitness components in a heterogeneous population&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Oikos&lt;/em&gt; 122: 739-753.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lebreton, J.-D. and O. Gimenez (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Lebreton_Gimenez_2013_JWM.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Detecting and estimating density-dependence in wildlife populations&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Widlife Management&lt;/em&gt; 77: 12-23.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez, O., Abadi, F., Barnagaud, J.-Y., Blanc, L., Buoro, M., Cubaynes, S., Desprez, M., Gamelon, M., Guilhaumon, F., Lagrange, P., Madon, B., Marescot, L., Papadatou, E., Papaïx, J., Péron, G., Servanty, S. (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/boulet-publi2012AnCons.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;How can quantitative ecology be attractive to young scientists? Balancing computer/desk work with field work&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Animal Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 16: 134-136.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bergeron, P., Montiglio, P.-O., Reale, D., Humphries, M., Gimenez, O. and D. Garant (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Bergeronetal2013.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Disruptive viability selection on adult exploratory behavior in eastern chipmunks&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Evolutionary Biology&lt;/em&gt; 26: 766-774.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blanc, L., E. Marboutin, S. Gatti, O. Gimenez (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Blancetal2012JWM.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Abundance of rare and elusive species: empirical investigation of closed vs. spatially explicit capture-recapture models with Lynx as a case study&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Wildlife Management&lt;/em&gt; 77: 372-378.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pettex, E., S.-H. Lorentsen, D. Grémillet, O. Gimenez, R.T. Barrett, J.-B. Pons, C. Le Bohec and F. Bonadonna (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Pettexetal2012.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Multi-scale foraging variability in northern gannet (Morus bassanus) fuels potential foraging plasticity&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Marine Biology&lt;/em&gt; 159: 2743-2756&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bauduin, S., J. Martin, H.H. Edwards, O. Gimenez, S. Koslovsky and D. Fagan (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Bauduinetal2013.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;An index of risk of co-occurrence between marine mammals and watercrafts: example of the Florida manatee&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biological Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 159: 127-136&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charpentier, M.J.E., Huchard, E., Widdig, A., Gimenez, O., Sallé, B., Kappelee, P. and J.P. Renoult (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Charpentieretal2012Ethology.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Distribution of affiliative behavior accross kin classes and their fitness consequences in mandrills&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ethology&lt;/em&gt; 118: 1198-1207&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez, O., Lebreton, J.-D., Gaillard, J.-M., Choquet, R. and R. Pradel (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenezetal2012TPB.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Estimating demographic parameters using hidden process dynamic models&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Theoretical Population Biology&lt;/em&gt; 82: 307-316. &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/codes/AppendixB.txt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buoro, M., E. Prévost, O. Gimenez (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Buoroetal2012JEB.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Digging through model complexity: using hierarchical models to uncover evolutionary processes in the wild&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Evolutionary Biology&lt;/em&gt; 25: 2077-2090&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hardouin, L. A., M. Nevoux, A. Robert, O. Gimenez and Y. Hingrat (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Hardouinetal_2012_Oikos.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Determinisms and costs of natal dispersal in a lekking species&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Oïkos&lt;/em&gt; 121: 804-812&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gamelon, M., Gaillard, J.-M., S. Servanty, O. Gimenez, C. Toïgo, E. Baubet, F. Klein, J.-D. Lebreton (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gamelon%20et%20al.%202012.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Making use of harvest information to examine alternative management scenarios: a body weight-structured model for wild boar&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Applied Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 49: 833-841.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Libois, E., O. Gimenez, D. Oro, E. Mínguez, R. Pradel, A. Sanz-Aguilar (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Liboisetal2012BiolCons.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Nest boxes: A successful management tool for the conservation of an endangered seabird&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biological Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 155: 39-43.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abadi, F., O. Gimenez, H. Jakobere, W. Stauberf, R. Arlettaz and M. Schaub (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Abadietal2012EcoMod.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Estimating the strength of density dependence in the presence of observation errors using integrated population models&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecological Modelling&lt;/em&gt; 242: 1-9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lebreton, J.-D., R. Choquet and O. Gimenez (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Lebreton%20et%20al%202011%20Biometrics.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Simple estimation and test procedures in capture-mark-recapture mixed models&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biometrics&lt;/em&gt; 68: 494-503.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cubaynes, S., C. Lavergne, E. Marboutin, and O. Gimenez (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Cubaynesetal2011MEE.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Assessing individual heterogeneity using model selection criteria: How many mixture components in capture-recapture models?&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 3: 564-573. &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/codes/Matlab%20codes.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frank, B., O. Gimenez and P. Baret (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Francketal2012-CanJFishAquatSci.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Assessing brown trout spawning movements with multistate capture-recapture models: a case study in a fully-controlled Belgian brook&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 69: 1091-1104&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Péron, G., Y. Ferrand, F. Gossmann, C. Bastat, M. Guenezan and O. Gimenez (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/P%C3%A9ronetal2012PopEcol.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Spatial heterogeneity in mortality and its impact on the population dynamics of Eurasian woodcocks&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Population Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 54: 305-312&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cubaynes, S, C. Doutrelant, A. Gregoire, P. Perret, B. Faivre, and O. Gimenez (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Cubaynesetal2012.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Testing hypotheses in evolutionary ecology with imperfect detection: Structural equation modeling of mark-recapture data&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 93: 248-255. &lt;a href=&#34;http://esapubs.org/archive/ecol/E093/024/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez, O., T. Anker-Nilssen and V. Grosbois (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenezetal2011MEE.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Exploring causal pathways in demographic parameter variation: Path analysis of mark-recapture data&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 3: 427-432. &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/codes/MEE3_150_sm_AppendixS1_S2.doc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choquet, R. and O. Gimenez (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Choquet%26Gimenez2011.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Towards built-in capture-recapture mixed models in program E-SURGE&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Ornithology&lt;/em&gt; 152: 625-639.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marescot, L., O. Gimenez, C. Duchamp, E. Marboutin and G. Chapron (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Marescotetal2012EcolModel.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Reducing matrix population models with application to social animal species&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecological Modelling&lt;/em&gt; 232: 91-96&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Papadatou, E., R. Pradel, M. Schaub, D. Dolch, H. Geiger, C. Ibañez, G. Kerth, A. Popa-Lisseanu, W. Schorcht, J. Teubner and O. Gimenez (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Papadatouetal2011Ecography.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Comparing survival among species with imperfect detection using multilevel analysis of mark-recapture data: a case study on bats&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecography&lt;/em&gt; 35: 153-161. &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/codes/e7084.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Praud, A., O. Gimenez, G. Zanella, B. Dufour, N. Pozzi, V. Antras, L. Meyer, B. Garin-Bastuji (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Praudetal2013.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Estimation of sensitivity and specificity of five serological tests for the diagnosis of porcine brucellosis&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Preventive Veterinary Medicine&lt;/em&gt; 104: 94-100&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaux, F., P.-Y. Henry and O. Gimenez (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Archauxetal2011.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;When can we ignore the problem of imperfect detection in comparative studies?&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 3: 188-194. &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/codes/MEE3_142_sm_AppendixS1.doc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Caniglia, R., E. Fabbri, S. Cubaynes, O. Gimenez, J.-D. Lebreton and E. Randi (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Caniglia%20et%20al.%202011_CoGe.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;An improved procedure to estimate wolf abundance using non-invasive genetic sampling and capture-recapture mixture models&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Conservation Genetics&lt;/em&gt; 13: 53-64&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fletcher, D., Lebreton, J.-D., Marescot, L., Schaub, M., Gimenez, O., Slooten, E. and S. Dawson (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Fletcheretal2011.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bias in estimation of adult survival and asymptotic population growth rate caused by undetected capture heterogeneity&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 3: 206-216&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buoro, M., O. Gimenez and E. Prévost (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Buoroetal2011.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Assessing adaptive phenotypic plasticity by means of conditional strategies from empirical data: The latent environmental threshold model&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 66: 996-1009. &lt;a href=&#34;http://datadryad.org/resource/doi:10.5061/dryad.ft612j0h&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gamelon, M., A. Besnard, J.-M. Gaillard, S. Servanty, E. Baubet, S. Brandt and O. Gimenez (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gamelonetal2011.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;High hunting pressure selects for earlier birth data: Wild boar as a case study&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 65: 3100-3112&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marescot, L., Pradel, R., Duchamp, C. Cubaynes, S., Marboutin, E., Choquet, R. Miquel, C. and O. Gimenez (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Marescotetal2011.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Capture-recapture population growth rate as a robust tool against detection heterogeneity for population management&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecological Applications&lt;/em&gt; 21: 2898-2907&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Péron, G., Y. Ferrand, F. Gossmann, C. Bastat, M. Guenezan and O. Gimenez (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Peronetal2011BES.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Escape migration decisions in Eurasian Woodcocks: insights from survival analyses using large-scale recovery data&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology&lt;/em&gt; 65: 1949-1955&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charmantier, A., M. Buoro, O. Gimenez and H. Weimerskirch (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Charmantieretal2011.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Heritability of short-scale natal dispersal in a large-scale foraging bird, the wandering albatross&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Evolutionary Biology&lt;/em&gt; 24: 1487-1496. &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/codes/JEB_2281_sm_AppendixS1-S2-FiguresS1-S2.doc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desprez, M. R. Pradel, E. Cam, J.-Y. Monnat and O. Gimenez (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Desprezetal2011.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Now you see him, now you don&amp;rsquo;t: Experience, not age, is related to reproduction in Kittiwakes&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 278: 3060-3066.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Madon, B., O. Gimenez, B. McArdle, C. Baker and C. Garrigue (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Madonetal2011.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;A New Method For Estimating Animal Abundance with Two Sources of Data in Capture-Recapture Studies&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 2: 390-400&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevoux, M., O. Gimenez, M. Nicoll, D. Arlt, C. Jones and K. Norris (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Nevouxetal2011.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Population regulation of territorial species: both site-dependence and interference mechanisms matter&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 278: 2173-2181&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Péron, G., Y. Ferrand, F. Gossmann, C. Bastat, M. Guenezan and O. Gimenez (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/P%C3%A9ron%20et%20al%202011%20Ecology%20-%20woodcock%20spatial%20regression.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Nonparametric spatial regression of survival probability: visualization of population sinks in Eurasian Woodcock&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 92: 1672-1679&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Servanty, S., J.-M. Gaillard, Ronchi, F., Focardi, S., Baubet E. &amp;amp; O. Gimenez (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Servantyetal-2011-JPE.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Influence of harvesting pressure on demographic tactics: implications for wildlife management&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Applied Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 48: 835–843&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fontaine, R., O. Gimenez and J. Bried (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Fontaineetal2011.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The impact of introduced predators, light-induced mortality of fledglings and poaching on the dynamics of the Cory’s shearwater (Calonectris diomedea) population from the Azores, northeastern subtropical Atlantic&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biological Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 144: 1998–2011&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marzolin, G., A. Charmantier and O. Gimenez (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Marzolinetal2010.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Frailty in state-space models: application to actuarial senescence in the dipper&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 92: 562-567. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.esapubs.org/archive/ecol/E092/048/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cubaynes, S., P. F. Doherty Jr, E. A. Schreiber, R. W. Schreiber and O. Gimenez (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Cubaynesetal2010BiolLetters.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;To breed or not to breed: seabirds response to extreme climatic events&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biology Letters&lt;/em&gt; 7: 303-306.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Papadatou, E. Ibáñez, C., Pradel, R. Juste, J. and O. Gimenez (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Papadatouetal2010Oecologia.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Assessing survival in a multi-population system: a case study on bat populations&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Oecologia&lt;/em&gt; 165: 925-933. &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/codes/442_2010_1771_MOESM2_ESM.doc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barnagaud, J.-Y., Crochet, P.-A., Magnani, Y., Bernard-Laurent, A., Menoni, E., Novoa, C. and O. Gimenez (2011). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Barnagaudetal2011JOrnitho.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Short-term response to the North Atlantic Oscillation but no long-term effects of climate change on the reproductive success of an alpine bird&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Ornithology&lt;/em&gt; 152: 631-641.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McCrea, R. S., B.J.T. Morgan, O. Gimenez, P. Besbeas, J.-D. Lebreton and T. Bregnballe (2010). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/McCrea2010_JABES.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Multi-site Integrated Population Modelling&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Agricultural, Biological, and Environmental Statistics&lt;/em&gt; 15: 539-561.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Papaïx, J., S. Cubaynes, M. Buoro, A. Charmantier, P. Perret and O. Gimenez (2010). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Papa%C3%AFxetal2010JEB.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Combining capture–recapture data and pedigree information to assess heritability of demographic parameters in the wild&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Evolutionary Biology&lt;/em&gt; 23: 2176-2184. &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/codes/JEB_2079_sm_DataS1.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Servanty, S., R. Choquet, E. Baubet, S. Brandt, J.-M. Gaillard, M. Schaub, C. Toïgo, J.-D. Lebreton, M. Buoro and O. Gimenez (2010). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Servantyetal2010Ecology.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Assessing whether mortality is additive using marked animals: a Bayesian state-space modeling approach&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 91: 1916–1923. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.esapubs.org/archive/ecol/E091/130/suppl-1.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besnard, A., Novoa, C. and O. Gimenez (2010). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Besnardetal2010WB.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hunting impact on Pyrenean gray partridge population dynamics&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Wildlife Biology&lt;/em&gt; 16: 135-143.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buoro, M., Prévost, E. and O. Gimenez (2010). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Buoroetal2010.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Investigating evolutionary trade-offs in wild populations of Atlantic salmon (Salmo salar): incorporating detection probabilities and individual heterogeneity&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 64: 2629-2642.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schaub, M. Aebischer, A. Gimenez, O., Berger, S. and R. Arlettaz (2010). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Schaub_etal_BiolCons2010.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Massive immigration balances high anthropogenic induced mortality in a stable eagle owl population: lessons for conservation&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biological Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 143: 1911–1918.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guilhaumon, F., Mouillot, D. and O. Gimenez (2010). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Guilhaumonetal2010.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;mmSAR: an R-package for multimodel species-area relationship inference&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecography&lt;/em&gt; 33: 420-424.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Péron, G. Gimenez, O., Charmantier, A., Gaillard, J.-M. and P.-A. Crochet (2010). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/P%C3%A9ronetal2010Proc.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Age at the onset of senescence in birds and mammals is predicted by early-life performance&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 277: 2849–2856.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez, O. and R. Choquet (2010). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenez%26Choquet2010Ecology.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Incorporating individual heterogeneity in studies on marked animals using numerical integration: capture-recapture mixed models&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 91: 951-957.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Péron, G., Crochet, P.A.C., Choquet, R., Pradel, R., Lebreton, J.-D. and O. Gimenez. (2010). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/P%C3%A9ronetal2010O%C3%AFkos.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Capture-recapture models with heterogeneity to study survival senescence in the wild&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Oïkos&lt;/em&gt; 119: 524-532. &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/codes/appPeronOikos.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Appendix&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cubaynes, S. Pradel, R. Choquet, R. Duchamp, C. Gaillard, J.-M., Lebreton, J.-D., Marboutin, E., Miquel, C., Reboulet, A.-M., Poillot, C., Taberlet, P. and O. Gimenez. (2010). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Cubaynesetal2010.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Importance of accounting for detection heterogeneity when estimating abundance: the case of French wolves&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Conservation Biology&lt;/em&gt; 24: 621-626.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abadi, F., Gimenez, O., Arlettaz, R. and M. Schaub (2010). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Abadi%20etal%20Ecology2010.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;An assessment of integrated population models: bias, accuracy, and violation of the assumption of independence&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 91: 7-14.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abadi, F., Gimenez, O., Ullrich, B., Arlettaz, R. and M. Schaub (2010). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Abadietal_JAppEco2010.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Estimation of immigration rate using integrated population models&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Applied Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 47: 393-400.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mihoub, J.-B., Gimenez, O., Pilard, P. and F. Sarrazin (2010). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Mihoubetal2010.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Challenging conservation of migratory species: Sahelian rainfalls drive first-year survival of the vulnerable Lesser Kestrel Falco naumanni&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biological Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 143: 839-847.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez, O., Grégoire, A. and T. Lenormand (2009). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenezetal2009Evolution.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Estimating and visualizing fitness surfaces using mark-recapture data&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Evolution&lt;/em&gt;. 63: 3097-3105. &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/codes/codesEvolution2009.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choquet, R., Lebreton, J.-D., Gimenez, O., Reboulet, A.-M., and R. Pradel. (2009). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Choquetetal2009UCARE.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;U-CARE: Utilities for performing goodness of fit tests and manipulating CApture-REcapture data&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecography&lt;/em&gt;. 32: 1071-1074.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kazakou, E., Violle, C, Roumet, C., Pintor, C., Gimenez, O. and E. Garnier. (2009). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Kazakouetal2009AnnalsofBotany.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Litter quality and decomposability of species from a Mediterranean succession depend on leaf traits but not on nitrogen supply&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Annals of Botany&lt;/em&gt; 104: 1151-1161&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grosbois, V., Harris, M. P., Anker-Nilssen, T., McCleery, R. H., Shaw, D. N., Morgan, B.J.T. and O. Gimenez (2009). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Grosboisetal2009Ecology.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Modeling survival at multi-population scales using mark-recapture data&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 90: 2922-2932. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.esapubs.org/archive/ecol/E090/208/suppl-1.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guilhaumon, F., O. Gimenez, K. J. Gaston, and D. Mouillot (2008). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Guilhaumonetal2009.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Reply to Bode and Murdoch: A proper integration of species-area relationship uncertainties into return on investment analyses is needed&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt;. 106: E13&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bischof, R., J. E. Swenson, N. G. Yoccoz, A. Mysterud, and O. Gimenez (2009). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Bischofetal2009.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The magnitude and selectivity of natural and multiple anthopogenic mortality causes in hunted brown bears&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Animal Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 78: 656-665.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mennerat, A., P. Perret, P. Bourgault, J. Blondel, O. Gimenez, D. W. Thomas, P. Heeb, M. M. Lambrechts (2009). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Menneratetal2009.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Aromatic plants in nests of blue tits: positive effects on nestlings&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Animal Behaviour&lt;/em&gt; 77: 569–574.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez, O., S. Bonner, R. King, R. A. Parker, S.P. Brooks, L. E. Jamieson, V. Grosbois, B. J. T. Morgan, and L. Thomas (2009). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenezetal2009WinBUGS.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;WinBUGS for Population Ecologists: Bayesian Modeling Using Markov Chain Monte Carlo Methods&lt;/a&gt;. In &lt;em&gt;Modeling Demographic Processes in Marked Populations&lt;/em&gt;. Thomson, D. L.; Cooch, E. G.; Conroy, M. J. (Eds.). Springer Series: Environmental and Ecological Statistics, Vol. 3, pages 883-915. &lt;a href=&#34;http://research-repository.st-andrews.ac.uk/handle/10023/677&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez, O., Morgan, B.J.T. and S.P. Brooks (2009). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenezetal2009-weakidentifiability.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Weak Identifiability in Models for Mark-Recapture-Recovery Data&lt;/a&gt;. In &lt;em&gt;Modeling Demographic Processes in Marked Populations&lt;/em&gt;. Thomson, D. L.; Cooch, E. G.; Conroy, M. J. (Eds.). Springer Series: Environmental and Ecological Statistics, Vol. 3, pages 1055-1067. &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/codes/code-overlap.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez, O. and C. Barbraud (2009). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenezetal2009-EES-splines.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Efficient Semiparametric Regression Modeling of Capture-Recapture Data: Assessing the Impact of Climate on Survival of Two Antarctic Seabird Species&lt;/a&gt;. In &lt;em&gt;Modeling Demographic Processes in Marked Populations&lt;/em&gt;. Thomson, D. L.; Cooch, E. G.; Conroy, M. J. (Eds.). Springer Series: Environmental and Ecological Statistics, Vol. 3, pages 43-58.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Borysiewicz, R.S., B.J.T. Morgan, V. Hénaux, T. Bregnballe, J-D. Lebreton, and O. Gimenez (2009). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Borysiewiczetal2009-EES-kalman.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;An Integrated Analysis of Multisite Recruitment, Mark-Recapture- Recovery and Multisite Census Data&lt;/a&gt;. In &lt;em&gt;Modeling Demographic Processes in Marked Populations&lt;/em&gt;. Thomson, D. L.; Cooch, E. G.; Conroy, M. J. (Eds.). Springer Series: Environmental and Ecological Statistics, Vol. 3, pages 579-591.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guilhaumon, F. O. Gimenez, K. J. Gaston, and D. Mouillot (2008). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Guilhaumon_Gimenez_Gaston_Mouillot_PNAS_2008.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Taxonomic &amp;amp; regional uncertainty in species-area relationships and the identification of richness hotspots&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt;. 105: 15458–15463.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez, O., A. Viallefont, A. Charmantier, R. Pradel, E. Cam, C. R. Brown, M. D. Anderson, M. Bomberger Brown, R. Covas, J.-M. Gaillard (2008). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenezetal-flawedinference-AmNat.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The risk of flawed inference in evolutionary studies when detectability is less than one&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;The American Naturalist&lt;/em&gt;. 172: 441–448.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez,O. (2008). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/commentGimenez2008CJS.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Discussion: Towards a Bayesian analysis template?&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;The Canadian Journal of Statistics&lt;/em&gt;. 36: 21-24.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grosbois V., Gimenez O., Gaillard, J.-M., Pradel, R., Barbraud, C., Clobert, J., Møller, A. P. and H. Weimerskirch (2008). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Grosboisetal2008.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Assessing the impact of climate variation on survival in vertebrate populations&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biological Reviews&lt;/em&gt; 83: 357-399.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pradel, R., L. Maurin-Bernier, O. Gimenez, M. Genovart, R. Choquet, and D. Oro (2008). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Pradeletal2007CanadianJournalofStatistics.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Estimation of sex-specific survival with uncertainty in sex assessment&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;The Canadian Journal of Statistics&lt;/em&gt; 36: 29-42.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charpentier, M.J.E., F. Prugnolle, O. Gimenez and A. Widdig (2008). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Charpentier%20et%20al%2008%20Behav%20Genet.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Genetic heterozygosity and sociality in a primate species&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Behavior Genetics&lt;/em&gt; 38: 151-158.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ghimire, S., Gimenez, O., Pradel, R., McKey, D., and Y. Aumeeruddy-Thomas (2008). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Ghimireetal2007JAE.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Demographic variation and population viability in a threatened Himalayan medicinal and aromatic herb (Nardostachys grandiflora): matrix modelling of harvesting effects in two contrasting habitats&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Applied Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 45: 41-51.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Véran, S., Gimenez, O., Flint, E., Kendall, B., Doherty, P., and J.-D. Lebreton (2007). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Veranetal2007JAppEcol.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Quantifying the impact of longline fisheries on adult survival in the Black-footed Albatross&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Applied Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 44: 942–952.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez, O., V. Rossi, R. Choquet, C. Dehais, B. Doris, H. Varella, J.-P. Vila and R. Pradel (2007). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenezetal2007EcologicalModelling.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;State-space modelling of data on marked individuals&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecological Modelling&lt;/em&gt; 206: 431-438. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vogelwarte.ch/code-for-running-bpa-using-jags.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schaub, M., Gimenez, O., Sierro, A. and R. Arlettaz (2007). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Schaubetal2007ConservationBiology.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Use of Integrated Modeling to Enhance Estimates of Population Dynamics Obtained from Limited Data&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Conservation Biology&lt;/em&gt; 21: 945–955. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vogelwarte.ch/code-for-running-bpa-using-jags.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kazakou, E., E. Garnier and Gimenez, O. (2007). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Kazakouetal2009AnnalsofBotany.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Contribution of leaf lifespan and nutrient resorption to mean residence time: an elasticity analysis&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 88: 1857-1863.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pinay, G., B. Gumiero, E. Tabacchi, O. Gimenez, A.M. Tabacchi-Planty, M.M. Hefting, T.P. Burt, V.A. Black, C. Nilsson, V. Iordache, F. Bureau, L. Vought, G.E. Petts and H. Décamps. (2007). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Pinayetal2007.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Patterns of denitrification rates in European alluvial soils under various hydrological regimes&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Freshwater Biology&lt;/em&gt; 52: 252–266.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez O., C. Crainiceanu, C. Barbraud, S. Jenouvrier and B.J.T. Morgan. (2006). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenezetal2006Biometrics.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Semiparametric regression in capture-recapture modelling&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biometrics&lt;/em&gt; 62: 691-698. &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/codes/splinesCMRenvironmental.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez, O., R. Covas, C. R. Brown, M. D. Anderson, M. Bomberger Brown and T. Lenormand. (2006). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenezetal2006Evolution.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Nonparametric estimation of natural selection on a quantitative trait using mark-recapture data&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 60: 460-466. &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/codes/splinesCMRindividual.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charpentier M., Peignot P., Hossaert-McKey M., Gimenez O., Setchell J. and E.J. Wickings (2005). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Charpentieretal2005BehavEcol.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Constraints on control: factors influencing reproductive success in male mandrils (Mandrillus sphinx)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Behavioral Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 16: 614-623.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do F.C., Goudiaby V.A., Gimenez O., Diagne A.L., Diouf M., Rocheteau A., Akpo L.E. (2005) &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Doetal2005ForEcolMan.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Environmental influence on canopy phenology in the dry tropics&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Forest Ecology and Management&lt;/em&gt;. 215: 319-328.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez O., Choquet R., Lamor L., Scofield P., Fletcher D., J.-D. Lebreton and R. Pradel (2005). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenezetal2005JABES.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Efficient Profile-Likelihood Confidence Intervals for Capture-Recapture Models&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Agricultural, Biological, and Environmental Statistics&lt;/em&gt; 10: 184-196.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pradel, R., Gimenez O. and J.-D. Lebreton (2005). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Pradeletal2005ABC.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Principles and interest of GOF tests for multistate capture-recapture models&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Animal Biodiversity and Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 28: 189–204.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ancrenaz M., Gimenez O., Ambu L., Ancrenaz K., Andau P., Goossens B., Payne J., Tuuga A. and I. Lackman- Ancrenaz (2005). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Ancrenazetal2005PlosBiol.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Aerial Survey Gives New Estimates for Orang-utans in Sabah, Malaysia&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Plos Biology&lt;/em&gt; 3: 30-37.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez O., Viallefont A., Choquet R., Catchpole E.A. and B.J.T. Morgan (2004). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenezetal2004ABC.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Methods for investigating parameter redundancy&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Animal Biodiversity and Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 27: 561-572.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choquet R., Reboulet A.-M., Pradel R., Gimenez O. and J.-D. Lebreton (2004). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Choquetetal2004ABC.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;M-SURGE: new software specically designed for multistate capture-recapture models&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Animal Biodiversity and Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 27: 207-215.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schaub M., Gimenez O., Schmidt B.R. and R. Pradel (2004). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Schaubetal2004Ecology.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Estimating survival and temporary emigration in the multistate capture-recapture framework&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 85: 2107-2113. &lt;a href=&#34;http://esapubs.org/archive/ecol/E085/061/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ancrenaz M., Goossens B., Gimenez O., Sawang A. and I. Lackman-Ancrenaz (2004). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Ancrenazetal2004AnimCons.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Determination of ape distribution and population size using ground and aerial surveys: a case study with orang-utans in lower Kinabatangan, Sabah, Malaysia&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Animal Conservation&lt;/em&gt; 7: 375-385.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charpentier M., Hossaert-McKey M., Peignot P., Gimenez O., Setchell J.M. and E.J. Wickings (2004). Social factors and male reproductive success in a highly sexually dimorphic primate: Paternity analysis over a 20 year period in a group of mandrills (Mandrillus sphinx). &lt;em&gt;Folia Primatologica&lt;/em&gt; 75: 244-245.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gimenez O., Choquet R. and J.-D. Lebreton (2003). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Gimenezetal2003BiomJ.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Parameter redundancy in multistate capture-recapture models&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biometrical Journal&lt;/em&gt; 45: 704-722. &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/codes/BiomJ.zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Codes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pradel R., Wintrebert C.M.A. and Gimenez O. (2003). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Pradeletal2003Biometrics.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;A proposal for a goodness-of-fit test to the Arnason-Schwarz multisite capture-recapture model&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Biometrics&lt;/em&gt; 59: 43-53.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besnard A., Gimenez O. and J.-D. Lebreton (2002). &lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Besnardetal2002EvolEcol.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;A model for the evolution of creching behaviour in gulls&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Evolutionary Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 16: 489-503.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Books and book chapters</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/publication/books/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/publication/books/</guid>
      <description>














&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-peyrard-n-and-gimenez-o-2022-statistical-approaches-for-hidden-variables-in-ecologyhttpswwwistecoukbookphpid1859-la-version-française-est-icihttpswwwistegroupcomfrproduitapproches-statistiques-pour-les-variables-cachees-en-ecologie&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/nath.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Peyrard N. and Gimenez O. (2022). 
Statistical Approaches for Hidden Variables in Ecology. La version française est 
ici.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/nath.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Peyrard N. and Gimenez O. (2022). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iste.co.uk/book.php?id=1859&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Statistical Approaches for Hidden Variables in Ecology.&lt;/a&gt; La version française est 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.istegroup.com/fr/produit/approches-statistiques-pour-les-variables-cachees-en-ecologie/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ici.&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;
















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-newman-kb-st-buckland-bjt-morgan-r-king-dl-borchers-dj-cole-p-besbeas-o-gimenez-and-l-thomas-2014-modelling-population-dynamics---model-formulation-fitting-and-assessment-using-state-space-methodshttpwwwspringercomstatisticslifesciencesmedicine26healthbook978-1-4939-0976-6&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/ken.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Newman, K.B., S.T. Buckland, B.J.T. Morgan, R. King, D.L. Borchers, D.J. Cole, P. Besbeas, O. Gimenez and L. Thomas (2014). 
Modelling Population Dynamics - Model Formulation, Fitting and Assessment using State-Space Methods.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/ken.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Newman, K.B., S.T. Buckland, B.J.T. Morgan, R. King, D.L. Borchers, D.J. Cole, P. Besbeas, O. Gimenez and L. Thomas (2014). 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.springer.com/statistics/life&amp;#43;sciences,&amp;#43;medicine&amp;#43;%26&amp;#43;health/book/978-1-4939-0976-6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Modelling Population Dynamics - Model Formulation, Fitting and Assessment using State-Space Methods.&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;
















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-king-r-bjt-morgan-o-gimenez-sp-brooks-2009-bayesian-analysis-of-population-ecologyhttpswwwmathsedacukrking33book-websiteindexhtml&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/ruth1.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;King, R., B.J.T. Morgan, O. Gimenez, S.P. Brooks (2009). 
Bayesian Analysis of Population Ecology.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/ruth1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    King, R., B.J.T. Morgan, O. Gimenez, S.P. Brooks (2009). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maths.ed.ac.uk/~rking33/Book-website/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bayesian Analysis of Population Ecology.&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;
















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-morrissey-mb-p-de-villemereuil-b-doligez-o-gimenez-2014-bayesian-approaches-to-the-quantitative-genetic-analysis-of-natural-populationspubs14-charmantier-chap14pdf-in-quantitative-genetics-in-the-wild-editors-a-charmantier-d-garant-and-leb-kruuk-oxford-university-press-pages-228-253&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/anne1.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Morrissey, M.B., P. de Villemereuil, B. Doligez, O. Gimenez (2014). 
Bayesian approaches to the quantitative genetic analysis of natural populations. In Quantitative Genetics in the Wild, Editors: A. Charmantier, D. Garant, and L.E.B. Kruuk. Oxford University Press, pages 228-253.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/anne1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Morrissey, M.B., P. de Villemereuil, B. Doligez, O. Gimenez (2014). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/14-Charmantier-Chap14.pdf&#34;&gt;Bayesian approaches to the quantitative genetic analysis of natural populations.&lt;/a&gt; In &lt;em&gt;Quantitative Genetics in the Wild&lt;/em&gt;, Editors: A. Charmantier, D. Garant, and L.E.B. Kruuk. Oxford University Press, pages 228-253.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;
















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-grosbois-v-and-o-gimenez-2010-capture-mark-recapture-modelspubsgrosbois26gimenez2010-bookanderspdf-in-effects-of-climate-change-on-birds-editors-ap-moller-w-fiedler-and-p-berthold-oxford-university-press-pages-39-46&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/anders1.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Grosbois V. and O. Gimenez (2010). 
Capture-mark-recapture models. In Effects of Climate Change on Birds, Editors: A.P. Moller, W. Fiedler and P. Berthold, Oxford University Press, pages 39-46.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/anders1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Grosbois V. and O. Gimenez (2010). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Grosbois%26Gimenez2010-bookAnders.pdf&#34;&gt;Capture-mark-recapture models.&lt;/a&gt; In &lt;em&gt;Effects of Climate Change on Birds&lt;/em&gt;, Editors: A.P. Moller, W. Fiedler and P. Berthold, Oxford University Press, pages 39-46.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;
















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-lebreton-j-d-e-klein-o-gimenez-and-f-rousset-2010-statistiques-pour-la-biologie-évolutivepubsstatistiques_20pour_la_biologie_20evolutivepdf-dans-biologie-evolutive-editeurs-thomas-f-lefèvre-t--raymond-m-de-boeck-editions-pages-33-48&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/m21.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Lebreton, J.-D., E. Klein, O. Gimenez and F. Rousset (2010). 
Statistiques pour la biologie évolutive. Dans Biologie Evolutive, Editeurs: Thomas F, Lefèvre T &amp;amp; Raymond M. De Boeck Editions, pages 33-48.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/m21.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Lebreton, J.-D., E. Klein, O. Gimenez and F. Rousset (2010). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Statistiques_%20pour_la_biologie_%20evolutive.pdf&#34;&gt;Statistiques pour la biologie évolutive.&lt;/a&gt; Dans &lt;em&gt;Biologie Evolutive&lt;/em&gt;, Editeurs: Thomas F, Lefèvre T &amp;amp; Raymond M. De Boeck Editions, pages 33-48.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;
















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-rouan-l-s-cubaynes-c-duchamp-c-miquel-a-m-reboulet-o-gimenez-j-d-lebreton-r-choquet-and-r-pradel-2010-modèles-de-mélange-en-capture-recapturepubsrouanetal2013pdf-dans-modèles-à-variables-latentes-et-modèles-de-mélange-editeurs-g-saporta-jj-droesbeke-and-c-thomas-agnan-editions-technip-pages-265-272&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/mixture1.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Rouan L., S. Cubaynes, C. Duchamp, C. Miquel, A.-.M. Reboulet, O. Gimenez, J.-D. Lebreton, R. Choquet and R. Pradel (2010). 
Modèles de mélange en capture-recapture. Dans Modèles à variables latentes et modèles de mélange, Editeurs: G. Saporta, J.J. Droesbeke and C. Thomas-Agnan, Editions Technip, pages 265-272.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/img/mixture1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Rouan L., S. Cubaynes, C. Duchamp, C. Miquel, A.-.M. Reboulet, O. Gimenez, J.-D. Lebreton, R. Choquet and R. Pradel (2010). 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://oliviergimenez.github.io/pubs/Rouanetal2013.pdf&#34;&gt;Modèles de mélange en capture-recapture.&lt;/a&gt; Dans &lt;em&gt;Modèles à variables latentes et modèles de mélange&lt;/em&gt;, Editeurs: G. Saporta, J.J. Droesbeke and C. Thomas-Agnan, Editions Technip, pages 265-272.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
